<chapter xml:id="installation"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
   xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude">

  <title>Installation</title>
  
  <section>
    <title>What do I Need?</title>
    
    <para>
      Description of the structure of our packages: Stratego/XT and
      language specific extensions (such as JavaFront).
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Stratego Shell
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Examples</title>
    
    <para>
      All the code examples in this manual are available for separate
      download, such that you can experiment based on these.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      <link xl:href="./examples.tar.gz">examples.tar.gz</link>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Instructions</title>
  
    <para>
      First of all download the required packages (.tar.gz, RPMs or
      Source RPMs). You need aterm and sdf2-bundle. The URLs are
      specified in the the release page of StrategoXT.
    </para>
    
    <section>
      <title>Using source tarballs</title>
      
      <section>
	<title>Installation of aterm and sdf2-bundle</title>
	
	<para>
	  The following sequence of commands takes care of building
	  and installing the aterm and the sdf2-bundle in
	  /usr/local.
	</para>
	
	<screen>
tar zxf aterm-<replaceable>version</replaceable>.tar.gz
cd aterm-<replaceable>version</replaceable>
./configure --with-gcc
make
make install
cd ..

tar zxf sdf2-bundle-<replaceable>version</replaceable>.tar.gz
cd sdf2-bundle-<replaceable>version</replaceable>
./configure
make
make install
cd ..
</screen>

          <para>
	    Configuring the aterm library --with-gcc limits the number
	    of different aterm libraries that are installed. Just
	    installing the gcc version makes installation of the aterm
	    library more portable and is sufficient for StrategoXT.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	    If you want to install the packages at a different
	    location, you should specify a --prefix in the configure
	    command. If you want to install the packages at two
	    different locations, you must configure the sdf2-bundle
	    with the location prefix aterm. For example:
	  </para>
	  
	  <screen>
./configure --prefix=/opt/aterm --with-gcc
./configure --prefix=/opt/sdf2-bundle --with-aterm=/opt/aterm
</screen>

	</section>

	<section>
	  <title>Installation of StrategoXT</title>

	  <para>
	    Unpack, configure, make and install StrategoXT using the
	    following commands:
	  </para>

	  <screen>
tar zxf strategoxt-<replaceable>version</replaceable>.tar.gz
cd strategoxt-<replaceable>version</replaceable>
./configure
make
make install
</screen>

	  <para>
	    If you want to install StrategoXT at a different prefix,
	    you should specify a --prefix. If you installed the aterm
	    library and the sdf2-bundle at a different location, you
	    should specify their location using --with-aterm and
	    --with-sdf. For example:
	  </para>

	  <screen>
./configure --prefix=/opt/strategoxt \
  --with-aterm=/opt/aterm --with-sdf=/opt/sdf2-bundle
</screen>

	</section>

      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Using binary RPMs</title>

	<para>
	  Install the RPMs by running the following command in the
	  directory where you've downloaded the RPMs.
	</para>

	<screen>
rpm -i *
</screen>

	<para>
	  Use the upgrade option if you've already installed earlier
	  versions of RPMs for aterm, strategoxt or the sdf2-bundle.
	</para>

	<screen>
rpm -U *
</screen>

	<para>
	  Of course you can also install the RPMs one by one by
	  specifying the filenames of the RPMs.  
	</para>

      </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
