<section xml:id="tutorial-overview"
   xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
   xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude">

  <title>Overview</title>

  <para>

    This tutorial gives an introduction to transformation with
    Stratego/XT by means of a number of examples that show typical
    ways of organizing transformation systems.

    The tutorial is divided into a number of parts, each part
    dedicated to a particular source language. For each language we
    show how to define its syntax, create a pretty-printer, and
    implement a number of transformations. In addition, we show which
    tools to use to generate parsers from syntax definitions, derive
    pretty-printers from syntax definitions, and compile
    transformation programs.

    The source code of the examples can be downloaded as well, so
    that you can repeat the experiments from the tutorial and add your
    own experiments.

  </para>
 
<section>
  <title>TIL: A Tiny Imperative Language</title>

  <para>
    The <link linkend="tutorial-til">first example</link> in the
    tutorial is a tiny imperative language (TIL), which has assignment
    statements, sequences of statements, and structured control-flow.
  </para>
 
  <para>
    For this simple language we define a complete syntax definition,
    and show how to generate from it a parser, signature, format
    checker, and pretty-print table. Based on these ingredients we
    explain how to create a typical transformation pipeline (without
    any transformations yet).
  </para>

  <para>
    Next we show how to define a number of typical transformations
    such as desugaring, bound variable renaming, interpretation, and
    data-flow transformations.
  </para>

</section>

<section>
  <title>BibTeX Transformations</title>

  <para>
    BibTeX is a small domain-specific data language for bibliographic
    information. It is included in the examples collection to show how
    Stratego/XT can be applied to document processing. In the 
    <link linkend="tutorial-bibtex">second part</link> of this tutorial
    we show the syntax definition for BibTeX and a number of
    transformations on BibTeX documents.
  </para>

</section>

  
<section>
  <title>To Do</title>

  <para>
    This tutorial is not complete. There are many other examples
    of applications of Stratego that are not (yet) covered by this
    tutorial, and countless more possible applications. Here are some
    examples:

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Analysis: check that variables are defined before use
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
           Typechecking: check that variables are used consistently
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Partial evaluation: specialize programs on specific inputs
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Custom pretty-printing
        </para>
      </listitem> 

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Configuration and deployment
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Domain-specific languages: implementation, compilation, optimization
        </para>
      </listitem> 

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Code generation: from specifications, high-level languages
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Language embedding and assimilation
        </para>
      </listitem>
 
    </itemizedlist>

    You are welcome to contribute examples, or requests for examples
    of particular types of applications.
  </para>

</section>

</section>
