<section
   xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
   xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude">

  <title>Software Transformations</title>

  <para>
    Program source code is the raw material produced by the software
    industry. Rather than being an end product, this material requires
    further processing to turn it into useful products. Compilation,
    program generation, domain-specific optimization and
    reverse-engineering are some examples of such processing.

    All these processes require the manipulation of program source
    code.  In fact, all such manipulations can be viewed as
    transformations of a program to a derived program. (Here the
    notion of `program' is interpreted broadly, and includes all kinds
    of artifacts used in the composition of software systems,
    including configuration and data files, as long as there contents
    conform to some formal language.) Hence, software transformation is
    the unifying notion underlying automatic program processing.
  </para>

  <para>
    To reach a higher level of automation in software engineering, the
    use of automatic software transformation is indispensable.
    However, the realization of software transformation systems is
    hard.  Parts of the process, such as parsing, are supported by
    generative techniques, but most aspects require hard work.  The
    effective implementation of software transformation systems is a
    barrier for the wide adoption of software transformation in
    software engineering.  Most transformation techniques used in
    practice are based on textual generation and manipulation, which
    poses limitations on what can be done and is error-prone.
  </para>

  <para>
    The examples contained in the next chapters show how to do software
    transformation in a structured and robust way.  They are all
    implemented using the Stratego/XT framework. This framework
    provides a versatile collection of transformation tools that can
    be applied to transformation of source code as well as documents.
    The goal of this example-based tutorial is to show how Stratego/XT is
    applied to practical problems, and is complimentary to the
    <link linkend="tutorial">Stratego/XT Tutorial</link>.
  </para>

</section>

