<chapter xml:id="svn-install"
   xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
   xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
   xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude">
  
  <title>Installation from Subversion</title>
  
  <para>
    Distribution (stable and continuous) are available from the
    download page at the Stratego/XT website. It is also possible to
    obtain the sources directly from Subversion. This is only useful
    if you want to modify the sources of Stratego/XT and might want to
    commit your changes.
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>Requirements</title>

    <para>
      Installation from Subversion requires some packages from the GNU
      build system. You need:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>Autoconf 2.58 or newer (2.57 will not do)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Automake 1.7.9 or newer. Very recent versions (1.9.x) are
	recommended and required if you want to create a distribution</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Libtool 1.5 or newer</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>pkg-config 0.15 or newer</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      Unfortunately, many Linux distributions contain old versions of
      these packages, so please check te versions that are installed
      on your system. Also, check that libtool is installed at the
      same location (prefix) as Automake, otherwise
      <command>aclocal</command> will not be able to find the Autoconf
      macros of Libtool (<filename>libtool.m4</filename>)
    </para>

    <para>
      You now need a baseline installation of Stratego/XT to install
      Stratego/XT from Subversion. The latest baseline is always
      available at the <link
      xl:href="ftp://ftp.stratego-language.org/pub/stratego/StrategoXT/baseline/latest/strategoxt.tar.gz">ftp
      server</link> of Stratego. The need for a baseline is explained
      in <xref linkend="baseline"/>. For the installation of the
      baseline, you can follow the ordinary installation instructions
      for end-users (<xref linkend="installation"/>).
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How to checkout</title>

    <para>
      The Stratego/XT sources are kept in a source repository managed by 
      Subversion. Before checking out, you need to install recent Subversion
      release. After you have done so, you may do a checkout using the following
      command:
    </para>

<screen>
  $ svn checkout https://svn.cs.uu.nl:12443/repos/StrategoXT/trunk/StrategoXT/
</screen>

    <para>
      Note that your Subversion client has to support SSL
      support. Install Subversion <option>--with-ssl</option>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How to install</title>

    <para>
      To bring the source tree into a state where you can follow the
      [[installation instructions]] you must run the =bootstrap=
      script (see also [[WhyBootstrap][why bootstrap]]).
	</para>

    <para>
      Note that on many distributions, the older versions of =automake=
      and =autoconf= are invoked by default.  You can check which version
      is invoked by issuing =automake --version= and =autoconf --version=.
      Unfortunately, the mechanism for switching to a newer version is 
      distribution-specific. We automatically figure this out for some 
      distributions. Look inside the boostrap for details, adjust and
      provide us with a patch, if your distribution is not supported. 
    </para>
          	
<screen>
  $ ./bootstrap
</screen>

    <para>
      Now you can proceed with the [[installation instructions]] for a
      Stratego/XT distribution, with one exception: you must configure
      Stratego/XT with your baseline installation:
      =--with-strategoxt=$baselineprefix=
    </para>

    <para>
      Historical note: in the past, a separate =make= and =make
      install= was not possible if you were installing for
      Subversion. This is no longer the case: you can use a separate
      and =make= and =make install= now we are using a baseline.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Subversion Repoman</title>

    <para>
      The repoman for gives an overview of possible ways to view the
      sources the StrategoXT repository:
    </para>

    <screen>https://svn.cs.uu.nl:12443/repoman/info/StrategoXT</screen>

  </section>
</chapter>
