<chapter xml:id="stratego-unit-testing"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude">

  
  <title>Unit Testing with SUnit</title>
  
  <para>
    StrategoUnit or SUnit is a Unit Testing framework for Stratego
    inspired by JUnit. The idea is to specify tests that apply a
    strategy to a specific term and compare the result to the expected
    output. The tests are combined into a test suite, which runs all
    tests and reports the number of successes and failures. When all
    tests pass, the program exits with status 0, otherwise it exists
    with status 1 to flag the error to the calling program, which is
    typically a makefile.
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>Setting up a test suite</title>
    
    <para>
      Module <filename>list-zip-test.str</filename> in the Stratego
      Standard Library is an example test suite. SUnit test suites can
      be compiled to an executable program. When run the program gives
      the following output:
    </para>
    
    <screen>
test suite: list-zip-test
nzip0-test
zip-test1
zip-test2
successes: 3
failures: 0
(3,0)
    </screen>

    <para>
      An extract from the module shows how a test suite can be set
      up:
    </para>

    <programlisting>
module list-zip-test
imports list-zip sunit
strategies

  main =
    test-suite(!"list-zip-test",
        nzip0-test;
        zip-test
     )

  nzip0-test =
    apply-test(!"nzip0-test"
        ,nzip0(id)
        ,!["a","b","c"]
        ,![(0, "a"), (1, "b"), (2, "c")]
        )
    </programlisting>
    
    <para>
      The test-suite strategy takes a string and a strategy. The
      strategy is typically a sequential composition of calls to unit
      tests. Unit tests such as <function>nzip0-test</function>
      are defined using one of the unit-test strategies from module
      <filename>sunit</filename>, which is in the standard library.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Compare expected and actual output</title>
    
    <para>
      The prototypical unit test is composed with the
      <function>apply-test</function> strategy, which takes a
      name, the strategy that is being tested, the input term, and the
      exptected output term. Note that the name, input, and output
      term must be specified in strategies, which means that if
      literal terms are used then you must build them using the !
      operator.
    </para>

    <programlisting>
apply-test(!"test3"
, ltS
, !("3","5")
, !("3","5")
)
    </programlisting>
  </section>
    
  <section>
    <title>Check for failure</title>
    
    <para>
      It is also useful to test that a strategy fails if applied to a
      certain input. The ordinary <function>apply-test</function>
      cannot be used for this because it requires an output term to
      which the result will be compared. For testing failure the
      <function>apply-and-fail</function> strategy is available in
      sunit. It ensures that the strategy fails if applied to a
      certain input.
    </para>

    <programlisting>
apply-and-fail(!"is-double-quote 3"
, is-double-quoted
, !"\"fnord"
)
    </programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Check arbitrary conditions on output</title>
    
    <para>
      Sometimes a test just want to check some condition on the output
      of a strategy application, without actually specifying the
      output itself. The <function>apply-test</function> strategy
      cannot be used for this because it performs an equivalence test
      of the required output and the actual output. In this case
      <function>apply-and-check</function> can be used. This
      strategy takes 4 arguments: a name, a strategy (s) to test, an
      input and a strategy that will be applied to the result of
      applying s to the input. This strategy must succeed if the
      output is correct, or fail if the output is incorrect.
    </para>
      
    <programlisting>
new-test =
  apply-and-check(!"new test",
    (new, new)
  , !(1, 1)
  , not(eq); (is-string, is-string)
  )
    </programlisting>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Unit testing with XTC</title>
    
    <para>
      XTC is the preferred system for writing components in Stratego/XT. Testing
      that an XTC component acts as intended is not much more difficult than
      for individual strategies. As the semantics of the interfaces to XTC 
      programs is open-ended, there is currently no generic testing
      framework for handling all the details.  
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Nevertheless, adapting the unit testing framework explained above for 
      testing your components is easy. Consider the strategy 
      <function>xtc-apply-test</function>, given below.
    </para>
    
    <programlisting>
xtc-apply-test(|nm, prog, args, inp, outp) =
  xtc-temp-files(
    apply-test(!nm,
        write-to
      ; xtc-transform(!prog, !args)
      ; read-from
    , !inp
    , !outp
    )
  )
    </programlisting>

    <para>
      This is a straightforward extension of <function>apply-test</function>. It
      will invoke the XTC program given in the <varname>prog</varname> term argument
      with the list of command line arguments in <varname>args</varname>. The input to the
      program is the term given by <varname>inp</varname>. The resulting term after
      <varname>prog</varname> has been run is checked against <varname>outp</varname>. 
      If they match, the test succeeds. 
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The simple code above does not account for additional file arguments to 
      <varname>prog</varname>. This may be useful if <varname>prog</varname> if 
      <varname>prog</varname> is, say, a pretty-printer which takes both a document
      and a style sheet as arguments. The code below provides an example of how
      this may be handled.
    </para>      
    
    <programlisting>
xtc-apply-pp-test(|nm, prog, ssheet, args, inp, outp) =
  xtc-temp-files(
    apply-test(!nm,
      where(&lt;print-to&gt; [ssheet] => FILE(f))
      ; write-to
      ; xtc-transform(!prog, &lt;concat&gt; [ args, "--stylesheet", f])
      ; read-from
    , !inp
    , !outp
    )
  )      
    </programlisting>
    
  </section>
      
</chapter>
